Guide to the Naturopathy collection, 1913-1975
Department of Special Collections
Naturopathy collection,
1913-1975
Special Collections M0759
Unknown
1 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1994.
Scope and Content
Materials dealing with the anti-fluoridation campaign, natural food and nutrition, natural healing and anti-organized medicine.
Access Terms
Hohensee, Adolphus.; Miller, Duon.; Health--religious aspects.; Medicine.; Nutrition--religious aspects.; Water--fluoridation--social aspects.; Vaccination.
Container List
- Series I: Anti-Fluoridation Campaign
  - Pro-fluoridation pamphlets [1954-1973] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Dental Association fluoride information packet [1952-1956] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scientific journals and conference proceedings [1938-1955] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Scientific journals and conference proceedings [1938-1955] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Medical doctors against fluoridation [1952-1956] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Medical doctors against flouridation [1956-1964] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous anti-fluoridation group fliers and factsheets [1953-1960] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous anti-fluoridation newsclippings, some annotated [1956-1962] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anti-fluoridation newsletters: (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Nation-Wide Campaigner (1954-1955)
    - News Behind the News (1958)
    - Pure Water News (1959-1960)
    - American Capsule News (1961)
  - Miscellaneous anti-fluoridation reprints, annotated articles [1936-1956] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - ------- [1957-1968] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - ------- Typed reprint series (1955-1956) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Community-based anti-fluoridation efforts: Chicago, New York City, Detroit, San Francisco, Grand Rapids (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Anti-fluoride pamphlets [1945-1963] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Anti-fluoride reports: (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Why Not to Fluoridate (1957)
    - Fluoridation of Public Water Supplies (1955)
    - Magnesium Deficiency and Fluorine (1967)
    - Facts You Should Know About Fluoridation (n.d.)
  - National Fluoridation News (1957-1968) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Anti-fluoridation special edition newspapers (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Binder containing miscellaneous anti-fluoridation clippings, letters, pamphlets (some duplication) (Box 2, Folder (1))
  - National Symposium on Fluoridation, 1966 (Box 2, Folder (2))
- Series II: Natural Food and Nutrition
  - Meat pamphlets and flier (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Pasteurization [1947-1955] (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sugar [1932-1959] (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chemical additives (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Vitamins (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Vitamin pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous nutrition articles, fliers [1950-1968] (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Nutrition pamphlets and leaflets (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - ------- (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - ------- (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - ------- (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Recipes (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Farming and soil [1939-1975] (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dr. Garten health and nutrition lecture series (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Health and nutrition products, gadgets, advertisements (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - ------- (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Organic Consumer Reports Health and consumer-awareness newsletter (April 6, 1965 - June 7, 1966) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - OCR (June 14, 1966 - December 26, 1967) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - OCR (January 2, 1968 - June 10, 1969) (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series III: Natural Healing / Anti-Organized Medicine
  - Traditional medical newsletters, articles [1949-1968] (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Neurological illustrations (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Anti-organized medicine and anti-socialized medicine material (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Anti-organized medicine pamphlets (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Phonograph record: "Highlights of a clinical investigation..." (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - National Christian Crusader (May 1956, July 1956, Feb. 1957) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Anti-vaccination fliers: smallpox, rabies, ethical issues of vaccination and relation to vivisection (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Anti-vaccination pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Anti-polio vaccination fliers (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Anti-polio pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Anti-polio vaccination: "Polio Prevention, Inc." National anti-vaccination group led by Duon Miller (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Hidden Dangers in Polio Vaccine and The Poisoned Needle, [n.d.] (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Cancer fliers, factsheets, letters [1963-1969] (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Cancel pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Sickle-cell anemia leaflets (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous disease pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Smoking and alcohol pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Toxemia, n.d., and toxemia pamphlet (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Anti-abortion and women's health flier and pamphlet (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Longevity guides (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Natural healing literature [1952-1961] (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Alternative health and medical treatment (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Back to Eden, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Doctors Speak Out (1965) and Health Secrets of Famous Doctors (1959) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Hair for All (1951) and Gastric and Duodenal Ulceration (1953) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Religious health pamphlets and guides (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Immanuel (1960) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Mental health pamphlets (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Flynn Health System (1913) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Natural Health Guardian (1958-1959) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Clifton's Food for Thot (1946-196-) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Natural Living (1941-1955) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Natural Health Federation letters, member forms (1955-1975) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Natural Health Federation Bulletin (1956-1969) (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Howard Inches Report (1959) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Milk and Meat (1974-1975) (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Annotated agenda of State Advisory Council (February 9-10, 1961) and letter organizing against council (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous envelopes, including addresses, to and from activist groups and individuals (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Health and Happiness Lecture Series, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Health and Happiness Lecture Series, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Health and Happiness Lecture Series, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Health and Happiness Lecture Series, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Health and Happiness Lecture Series, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Recommended reading lists and purchase order forms. Primarily health related, some religious and political material. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Recommended reading lists and purchase order forms. Primarily health related, some religious and political material. (Box 6, Folder 7)